<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY message_reference SYSTEM "messages_as_db.xml">
]>
<article lang="en">
	<articleinfo>
		<title>OpenSCADA DA NET interface specification</title>
		<author>
			<firstname>Jens</firstname>
			<surname>Reimann</surname>
			<email>jens.reimann@inavare.net</email>
		</author>
		<copyright><year>2006</year><holder>TH4 SYSTEMS GmbH</holder></copyright>
		<legalnotice>
			<para>
    Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
    under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
    or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
    with Invariant Sections beeing <xref linkend="overview"/>,
    with the Front-Cover Texts being
    <quote>OpenSCADA DA NET interface specification</quote>, and no Back-Cover Texts.
    A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
    Free Documentation License".
           </para>
		</legalnotice>
	</articleinfo>
  
  <sect1 id="overview"><title>Overview and Purpose</title>
  	<para>
  		This document describes the OpenSCADA DA NET interface.
  	</para>
  	<para>
  		This document currently is a <emphasis>work in progress</emphasis> so expect
  		this specification to change.
  	</para>
  	
    <sect2><title>About</title>
    
      <sect3><title>About OpenSCADA</title>
        <para>
          The OpenSCADA project aims to create a <emphasis>state of the art</emphasis>
          SCADA system.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3><title>About OpenSCADA DA</title>
        <para>
          The <abbrev>DA</abbrev> (Data Access) interface of OpenSCADA focuses
          on accessing data.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3><title>About OpenSCADA DA NET</title>
        <para>
          The OpenSCADA DA NET interface is the DA interface based on the protocol
          <abbrev>GMPP</abbrev>.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2><title>Purpose</title>
      <para>
        This document specifies the OpenSCADA DA NET interface. It explains
        the basic prinicples of the interface, lists the messages exchanged
        between peers. 
      </para>
      <para>
        The information in this document is needed for creating a new
        implementation of the OpenSCADA DA NET interface. This might be
        necessary if you want to use a programming language which is
        currently not covered by the existing implementations.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2><title>Target audience</title>
      <para>
        The target audience are people who are interested in creating their own
        implementation of the OpenSCADA DA NET interface. Although there are
        reference implementations it might be of interest for someone to create
        its own implementation (e.g. unsupported programming languages,
        license problems with open source licenses, etc).
      </para>      
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1><title>The big picture</title>
    <para>
      In order to understand what exactly the OpenSCADA DA NET interface is you will
      need to understand the <quote>big picture</quote> of the interfaces of OpenSCADA.
    </para>
    <para>
      The idea for OpenSCADA is to be as independent and open as possible. So the target
      is that also for the interfaces of the different components it should be possible
      to exchange the interface itself.
    </para>
    
    <sect2><title>Levels of interfacing</title>
    <para>
      In order to achieve this the interfaces are splitted up in two levels.
      <variablelist>
      
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Level 0 interface</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This is the lowest level. Normally neutral to the programming language
              used for implementing the interface.
            </para>
            <para>
              A level 0 interface specification contains:
              
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>A communication layer</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>A description how the communication layer is used</para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
              
              <example><title>Examples of Level 0 communication layers</title>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>GMPP</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Corba</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>WebService</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </example>
              
              <example><title>Examples of Level 0 communication layer descriptions</title>
                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>GMPP</term>
                    <listitem><para>Message specification</para></listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>Corba</term>
                    <listitem><para>IDL of interface</para></listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>WebService</term>
                    <listitem><para>WebService description</para></listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
              </example>
              
              
            </para>
            
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Level 1 interface</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The level 1 interface is the programming language bound interface.
              So for example you might have a level 1 interface for progamming
              language you have (Java, C++, ...).
            </para>
            <note>
              <para>
                In some cases <emphasis>programming language dependant</emphasis>
                might not be correct. For example both Java and .NET are based on
                a virtual machine which executes the generated code. Both
                Java and .NET have different compilers that compile different
                programming languages to one VM-code they can reuse modules inside
                their framework.
              </para>
              <para>
                For example Java (the framework) has Java (the programming
                language and Groovy. Creating an implementation in Java would
                allow Groovy to re-use the code since it is based on the same
                virtual machine. Also for .NET you have C# and VB.NET which
                share the same base. So an implementation in C# would be
                available in VB.NET.
              </para>
              <para>
                To keep it simple the following sections will refer use <quote>
                programming language dependant</quote> but in some cases might
                mean <quote>framework dependant</quote>.
              </para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        
      </variablelist>
      This results in two levels. One that is communication layer specific but
      programming language indepedant. And one that is communication layer
      independant but programming langage specific.
    </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2><title>Level 0 implementations</title>
      <para>
        A level 0 implementation is the merger of the both level 0 and level 1 interface.
        So by using the level 0 interface specification you implement the level 1 interface
        itself (e.g. you implement the Java interface by using the GMPP interface
        specification for OpenSCADA DA).
      </para>
      <para>
        For example using the Level 0 interface <quote>OpenSCADA DA NET</quote>
        you implement the <quote>OpenSCADA DA Java</quote> interface.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2><title>Different sides</title>
      <para>
        In most cases you will have differnt sides of an interface (e.g. OpenSCADA DA
        has a client and server side). There should be no difference at the level 0
        interface (e.g. with Corba the IDL is the same for both server and client,
        only the client will use the Proxy classes whereas the server side implements
        the Corba interfaces).
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2><title>The choice</title>

      <para>
        What to use when:
      </para>
      
      <sect3><title>You want to create a client application for OpenSCADA</title>
        <para>
          When creating a client you normally will choose a programming language
          and stick with that.
        </para>
        <para>
          So you don't care about the way of communication and select a level 1
          interface which you use as interface to OpenSCADA.
        </para>
        <para>
          For example you use <quote>OpenSCADA DA Java</quote> when developing
          your application. Later when running you select the
          <quote>OpenSCADA DA NET Java</quote> implementation.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3><title>You want to create a server application for OpenSCADA</title>
        <para>
          Actually this is the same scenario as when creating client application.
          Based on your programming language you pick the level 1 interface and
          later when running let the user choose the level 0 implementation.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3><title>You have a server and want to access it</title>
        <para>
          You have a server application and some client that want to access it.
        </para>
        <para>
          Select what communication layer fits best for your needs and run
          both client and server with that level 0 implemenation.
        </para>
        <para>
          For example server and client are written in Java and both use the
          <quote>OpenSCADA DA Java</quote> level 1 interface. You then choose
          <quote>OpenSCADA DA NET Java</quote> as level 0 implemenation because
          you need a client/server based protocol to tunnel through your firewall.
        </para>
        <para>
          On the other side you could also choose <quote>OpenSCADA DA Corba Java
          </quote> because your like Corba more.
        </para>
        <para>
          Or you choose <quote>OpenSCADA DA XXX Java</quote> because ...
        </para>
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3><title>You want to bring OpenSCADA to a new programming language</title>
        <para>
          First check if you can re-use existing implementations. For example if
          you have implementations for Java and look for a Groovy interface you
          can reuse the Java interface since the base on the same virtual machine.
          The same is true for C# and VB.NET on the .NET Framework or on Mono.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you cannot re-use an existing implemenation you need to take a three
          step approach:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Ensure that the communication layer of the level 0 interface
                exists for your environment or implement it.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Design a level 1 interface for your programming language. It
                should be close the already existing interface in order
                to aid others using it.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Implement the level 1 interface in your programming language
                by using the communication layer and specification of the
                level 0 interface.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3><title>When do I have to create a new level 0 interface</title>
        <para>
          This question is a little bit harder to answer. Hopefully never because
          all level 0 interfaces should be provided by the OpenSCADA project itself.
          The plan is to have level 0 interfaces for: GMPP, Corba and WebServices.
          Which should cover most needs.
        </para>
        <para>
          However there are also other interesting technologies which could be used
          as communication layer between OpenSCADA modules: Java RMI,
          ICE (<ulink url="http://www.zeroc.com/">http://www.zeroc.com/</ulink>),
          and maybe a dozen more.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1><title>OpenSCADA DA NET</title>
    <para>
      This section specifies that <quote>OpenSCADA DA NET</quote> interface.
    </para>
    
    <sect2><title>Communication layer</title>
      <para>
        As communication layer <quote>GMPP</quote> is used. For the description
        of <quote>GMPP</quote> itself see the <quote>GMPP protocol specification</quote>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Since GMPP is used there are two distinct peers. A client and a server.
        The definition of client and server in GMPP are analogue to the definition
        of client and server in OpenSCADA. So the OpenSCADA client is also the GMPP client.
      </para>
      <para>
        GMPP allows a session oriented communication. The GMPP session must be bound
        to the OpenSCADA DA session. When the GMPP session is closed (e.g. manual disconnect,
        broken link, etc) also the OpenSCADA session must be closed.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2><title>Message Reference</title>
      <para>
        The following sections describe the messages used in the
        <quote>OpenSCADA DA NET</quote> interface.
      </para>
      &message_reference;
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <appendix><title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>
  	<para>
  		<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
		GNU Free Documentation License
		  Version 1.2, November 2002


 Copyright (C) 2000,2001,2002  Free Software Foundation, Inc.
     51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA  02110-1301  USA
 Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies
 of this license document, but changing it is not allowed.


0. PREAMBLE

The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or other
functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom: to
assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it,
with or without modifying it, either commercially or noncommercially.
Secondarily, this License preserves for the author and publisher a way
to get credit for their work, while not being considered responsible
for modifications made by others.

This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that derivative
works of the document must themselves be free in the same sense.  It
complements the GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft
license designed for free software.

We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for free
software, because free software needs free documentation: a free
program should come with manuals providing the same freedoms that the
software does.  But this License is not limited to software manuals;
it can be used for any textual work, regardless of subject matter or
whether it is published as a printed book.  We recommend this License
principally for works whose purpose is instruction or reference.


1. APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS

This License applies to any manual or other work, in any medium, that
contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be
distributed under the terms of this License.  Such a notice grants a
world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use that
work under the conditions stated herein.  The "Document", below,
refers to any such manual or work.  Any member of the public is a
licensee, and is addressed as "you".  You accept the license if you
copy, modify or distribute the work in a way requiring permission
under copyright law.

A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work containing the
Document or a portion of it, either copied verbatim, or with
modifications and/or translated into another language.

A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter section of
the Document that deals exclusively with the relationship of the
publishers or authors of the Document to the Document's overall subject
(or to related matters) and contains nothing that could fall directly
within that overall subject.  (Thus, if the Document is in part a
textbook of mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any
mathematics.)  The relationship could be a matter of historical
connection with the subject or with related matters, or of legal,
commercial, philosophical, ethical or political position regarding
them.

The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections whose titles
are designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the notice
that says that the Document is released under this License.  If a
section does not fit the above definition of Secondary then it is not
allowed to be designated as Invariant.  The Document may contain zero
Invariant Sections.  If the Document does not identify any Invariant
Sections then there are none.

The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that are listed,
as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that says that
the Document is released under this License.  A Front-Cover Text may
be at most 5 words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25 words.

A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a machine-readable copy,
represented in a format whose specification is available to the
general public, that is suitable for revising the document
straightforwardly with generic text editors or (for images composed of
pixels) generic paint programs or (for drawings) some widely available
drawing editor, and that is suitable for input to text formatters or
for automatic translation to a variety of formats suitable for input
to text formatters.  A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file
format whose markup, or absence of markup, has been arranged to thwart
or discourage subsequent modification by readers is not Transparent.
An image format is not Transparent if used for any substantial amount
of text.  A copy that is not "Transparent" is called "Opaque".

Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain
ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML
or XML using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple
HTML, PostScript or PDF designed for human modification.  Examples of
transparent image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG.  Opaque formats
include proprietary formats that can be read and edited only by
proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which the DTD and/or
processing tools are not generally available, and the
machine-generated HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by some word
processors for output purposes only.

The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page itself,
plus such following pages as are needed to hold, legibly, the material
this License requires to appear in the title page.  For works in
formats which do not have any title page as such, "Title Page" means
the text near the most prominent appearance of the work's title,
preceding the beginning of the body of the text.

A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named subunit of the Document whose
title either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in parentheses following
text that translates XYZ in another language.  (Here XYZ stands for a
specific section name mentioned below, such as "Acknowledgements",
"Dedications", "Endorsements", or "History".)  To "Preserve the Title"
of such a section when you modify the Document means that it remains a
section "Entitled XYZ" according to this definition.

The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice which
states that this License applies to the Document.  These Warranty
Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in this
License, but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other
implication that these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has
no effect on the meaning of this License.


2. VERBATIM COPYING

You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either
commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the
copyright notices, and the license notice saying this License applies
to the Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no other
conditions whatsoever to those of this License.  You may not use
technical measures to obstruct or control the reading or further
copying of the copies you make or distribute.  However, you may accept
compensation in exchange for copies.  If you distribute a large enough
number of copies you must also follow the conditions in section 3.

You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above, and
you may publicly display copies.


3. COPYING IN QUANTITY

If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly have
printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the
Document's license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the
copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover
Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on
the back cover.  Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify
you as the publisher of these copies.  The front cover must present
the full title with all words of the title equally prominent and
visible.  You may add other material on the covers in addition.
Copying with changes limited to the covers, as long as they preserve
the title of the Document and satisfy these conditions, can be treated
as verbatim copying in other respects.

If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit
legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent
pages.

If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document numbering
more than 100, you must either include a machine-readable Transparent
copy along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each Opaque copy
a computer-network location from which the general network-using
public has access to download using public-standard network protocols
a complete Transparent copy of the Document, free of added material.
If you use the latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps,
when you begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure
that this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the stated
location until at least one year after the last time you distribute an
Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or retailers) of that
edition to the public.

It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors of the
Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to give
them a chance to provide you with an updated version of the Document.


4. MODIFICATIONS

You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document under
the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you release
the Modified Version under precisely this License, with the Modified
Version filling the role of the Document, thus licensing distribution
and modification of the Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy
of it.  In addition, you must do these things in the Modified Version:

A. Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct
   from that of the Document, and from those of previous versions
   (which should, if there were any, be listed in the History section
   of the Document).  You may use the same title as a previous version
   if the original publisher of that version gives permission.
B. List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or entities
   responsible for authorship of the modifications in the Modified
   Version, together with at least five of the principal authors of the
   Document (all of its principal authors, if it has fewer than five),
   unless they release you from this requirement.
C. State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the
   Modified Version, as the publisher.
D. Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document.
E. Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications
   adjacent to the other copyright notices.
F. Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license notice
   giving the public permission to use the Modified Version under the
   terms of this License, in the form shown in the Addendum below.
G. Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant Sections
   and required Cover Texts given in the Document's license notice.
H. Include an unaltered copy of this License.
I. Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its Title, and add
   to it an item stating at least the title, year, new authors, and
   publisher of the Modified Version as given on the Title Page.  If
   there is no section Entitled "History" in the Document, create one
   stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the Document as
   given on its Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified
   Version as stated in the previous sentence.
J. Preserve the network location, if any, given in the Document for
   public access to a Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise
   the network locations given in the Document for previous versions
   it was based on.  These may be placed in the "History" section.
   You may omit a network location for a work that was published at
   least four years before the Document itself, or if the original
   publisher of the version it refers to gives permission.
K. For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications",
   Preserve the Title of the section, and preserve in the section all
   the substance and tone of each of the contributor acknowledgements
   and/or dedications given therein.
L. Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document,
   unaltered in their text and in their titles.  Section numbers
   or the equivalent are not considered part of the section titles.
M. Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements".  Such a section
   may not be included in the Modified Version.
N. Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled "Endorsements"
   or to conflict in title with any Invariant Section.
O. Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.

If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or
appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material
copied from the Document, you may at your option designate some or all
of these sections as invariant.  To do this, add their titles to the
list of Invariant Sections in the Modified Version's license notice.
These titles must be distinct from any other section titles.

You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it contains
nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various
parties-for example, statements of peer review or that the text has
been approved by an organization as the authoritative definition of a
standard.

You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text, and a
passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the list
of Cover Texts in the Modified Version.  Only one passage of
Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or
through arrangements made by) any one entity.  If the Document already
includes a cover text for the same cover, previously added by you or
by arrangement made by the same entity you are acting on behalf of,
you may not add another; but you may replace the old one, on explicit
permission from the previous publisher that added the old one.

The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this License
give permission to use their names for publicity for or to assert or
imply endorsement of any Modified Version.


5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS

You may combine the Document with other documents released under this
License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for modified
versions, provided that you include in the combination all of the
Invariant Sections of all of the original documents, unmodified, and
list them all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in its
license notice, and that you preserve all their Warranty Disclaimers.

The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and
multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single
copy.  If there are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but
different contents, make the title of each such section unique by
adding at the end of it, in parentheses, the name of the original
author or publisher of that section if known, or else a unique number.
Make the same adjustment to the section titles in the list of
Invariant Sections in the license notice of the combined work.

In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled "History"
in the various original documents, forming one section Entitled
"History"; likewise combine any sections Entitled "Acknowledgements",
and any sections Entitled "Dedications".  You must delete all sections
Entitled "Endorsements".


6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS

You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other documents
released under this License, and replace the individual copies of this
License in the various documents with a single copy that is included in
the collection, provided that you follow the rules of this License for
verbatim copying of each of the documents in all other respects.

You may extract a single document from such a collection, and distribute
it individually under this License, provided you insert a copy of this
License into the extracted document, and follow this License in all
other respects regarding verbatim copying of that document.


7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS

A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other separate
and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a storage or
distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the copyright
resulting from the compilation is not used to limit the legal rights
of the compilation's users beyond what the individual works permit.
When the Document is included in an aggregate, this License does not
apply to the other works in the aggregate which are not themselves
derivative works of the Document.

If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these
copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of
the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be placed on
covers that bracket the Document within the aggregate, or the
electronic equivalent of covers if the Document is in electronic form.
Otherwise they must appear on printed covers that bracket the whole
aggregate.


8. TRANSLATION

Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section 4.
Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special
permission from their copyright holders, but you may include
translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition to the
original versions of these Invariant Sections.  You may include a
translation of this License, and all the license notices in the
Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers, provided that you also include
the original English version of this License and the original versions
of those notices and disclaimers.  In case of a disagreement between
the translation and the original version of this License or a notice
or disclaimer, the original version will prevail.

If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements",
"Dedications", or "History", the requirement (section 4) to Preserve
its Title (section 1) will typically require changing the actual
title.


9. TERMINATION

You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document except
as expressly provided for under this License.  Any other attempt to
copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the Document is void, and will
automatically terminate your rights under this License.  However,
parties who have received copies, or rights, from you under this
License will not have their licenses terminated so long as such
parties remain in full compliance.


10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE

The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions
of the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time.  Such new
versions will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may
differ in detail to address new problems or concerns.  See
http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/.

Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version number.
If the Document specifies that a particular numbered version of this
License "or any later version" applies to it, you have the option of
following the terms and conditions either of that specified version or
of any later version that has been published (not as a draft) by the
Free Software Foundation.  If the Document does not specify a version
number of this License, you may choose any version ever published (not
as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.
]]>
  		</programlisting>
  	</para>
  </appendix>
  
</article>
