<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" []>

<sect1 id="introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
		The following sections give you a short introduction into OpenSCADA.   		
  	</para>
  	
  	<sect2 id="overview"><title>Overview and Purpose</title>
	<para>
  		This document describes the different components of OpenSCADA from a users point of view.
  	</para>
  	</sect2>
  	
<sect2 id="quickStart"><title>Quick Start</title>
	<para>
	This section is intended to give you a really quick start in some of the
	<trademark>OpenSCADA</trademark> functionality.
	</para>
 		
<sect3><title>Test Client</title>
	<para>
	There is a test client called <filename>OSTC</filename>. Its purpose is to aid testing
	and performing generic tasks. It is not a <quote>end user client</quote>.
	</para>
	
	<sect4><title>Installation &amp; setup</title>
	
	<para>
	See section <xref linkend="ostc_install"/> on how to install <filename>OSTC</filename>.
	Once you have it up and running perform the following steps:
	
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		<para>Start the application</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para>Switch to the <quote>DA</quote> perspective</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para>Right click on the <quote>Default File Source</quote> entry in
		the <quote>Navigator</quote></para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para>Add two new URIs: <uri>da:net://localhost:1202</uri> and <uri>da:net://localhost:1203</uri>
		</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para>
		Start the two simulation servers from the <quote>Testing</quote> menu
		<footnote>
		<para>The two test servers use the TCP port number 1202 and 1203. You need to ensure that
		the application has the permissions by the operating system (or your local firewall) to open
		these ports in listen mode. Also you need to ensure that these ports are available and not used
		by other applications. You can change the port numbers in the preferences dialog.
		</para>
		</footnote>
		</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		<para>Right click on the previously created <acronym>URI</acronym> entries and
		issue the <quote>Connect</quote> command
		</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	
	You can now browse through the items provided by the connected DA server.
	</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Playing with the memory items</title>
	<para>
	There are some <quote>memory items</quote> which can be used to play around with. Data written
	to these items will be feed in back as input. These items support both read and write operations.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	<itemizedlist>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>Ensure that are switched to the DA perspective and have one real time list and the
	navigator visible. Also ensure that you have the testing servers running as described earlier.</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>Open the connection to <uri>da:net://localhost:1203</uri></para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>Navigate to the <filename>memory</filename> folder and right click on the
	<filename>control</filename> item.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>Issue a write command and write a positive integer number not too big (e.g. 10)</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>After the write command there should appear exactly the amount of memory items
	you requested in your write command</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>Drag and drop some of these new items to the real time list. They should appear in
	the real time list with the ID <filename>memory-cell-X</filename> where X is the
	number of the memory item used.
	</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>The items in the real time list should have the status <quote>CONNECTED</quote>
	and a value of <quote>NULL</quote>
	</para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	<para>Right click on one item in the real time list and issue another write command.
	Write any value you like. The value should be provided by the data item after the
	write command completed</para>
	</listitem>
	
	</itemizedlist>
	
	This gives you a short introduction on how to read a write data from a DA server.
	</para>
	
</sect4>

</sect3>
 		
</sect2>
  	
</sect1>